<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="Pueblo of Picuris Tribal Council Res. No. 2025-008">
  <num>2025-008</num>
  <heading>ADOPTION OF PUEBLO OF PICURIS TRIBAL LAW AND ORDER CODE</heading>
  <meta>
    <effective>2025-03-11</effective>
    <history>
      <adopted>2025-03-11</adopted>
    </history>
    <citations>
      <citation type="res" url="./adopted/2025-008.pdf">Res. No. 2025-008</citation>
    </citations>
  </meta>
  <recitals>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text> Picuris Pueblo ("Pueblo") is a sovereign and self-governing Tribe, recognized as such by the United States of America with the authority to govern its people, lands and other resources, and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text> the Picuris Pueblo Tribal Council ("Tribal Council") is the duly constituted governing body acting with authority for the Pueblo and responsible for its people in its exercise of sovereign governmental powers, and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text> this resolution is passed in exercise of the responsibilities and authorities of the Tribal Council for and in the best interest of the Picuris Pueblo, and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text> the Tribal Council is committed to fulfilling their responsibility to protect and promote public safety within the jurisdiction of Picuris Pueblo, and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text> for the convenience of community members and governmental operations, and to enhance economic opportunity and investment, the Pueblo desires to publish its resolutions and other laws of general applicability on the Internet, and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text> the Pueblo has worked with Open Law Library ("OLL") to recodify the Tribe's resolutions and publish them in a new electronic tribal law library at https://law.picurispueblo.org, and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text> OLL is a 501 (c)(3) non-profit with the mission to help governments make all their official laws freely and openly accessible to the public in human and computer readable formats, and OLL develops and maintains software systems for the performance of this mission, and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>	OLL's software is capable of ensuring that the published code is:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Preservable - All published laws will be maintained in a manner that meets or exceeds all requirements for level 2 preservation as specified by the National Digital Stewardship Alliance,</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Authenticatable - All published laws will be authenticatable as the official laws of the Tribe. Authentication will use Open Law Library certificates, and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>Accessible - All published laws will be available to the public through OLL or the Tribe indefinitely.</text>
      </para>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text> the Pueblo, as part of establishing its new online Pueblo of Picuris Law Library, intends to recodify the current Pueblo of Picuris Tribal Law and Order Code as the Pueblo of Picuris Tribal Law and Order Code. This codification includes reorganizing and renumbering prior resolutions and codes; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text> the Pueblo wishes to make the Pueblo of Picuris Tribal Law and Order Code the official version of the Tribe's resolutions.</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>THEREFORE BE IT RESOLVED,</conjunction>
      <text> that the Pueblo:</text>
    </recital>
  </recitals>
  <section>
    <num>1</num>
    <heading>Recodification</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>hereby codifies its current resolutions and code as the Pueblo of Picuris Tribal Law and Order Code; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>this codification reorganizes and consolidates the existing Pueblo resolutions by subject area into titles and chapters. Pueblo resolutions shall be reorganized, and renumbered appropriately, into the following Titles:</text>
      <text>
        <ul>
          <li>Title 1 – General Provisions</li>
          <li>Title 2 – Rules of Civil Procedure</li>
          <li>Title 3 – Rules of Criminal Procedure</li>
          <li>Title 4 – Criminal Justice</li>
          <li>Title 5 – Traffic Safety</li>
          <li>Title 6 – Domestic Relations</li>
          <li>Title 7 – Domestic Violence</li>
          <li>Title 8 – Exclusion and Removal</li>
          <li>Title 9 – Game and Fish</li>
          <li>Title 10 – Children</li>
          <li>Title 11 – Integrated Solid Waste Management</li>
          <li>Title 12 – Medical Cannabis</li>
          <li>Title 13 – Elder and Vulnerable Adult Protection</li>
          <li>Title 14 – Probate</li>
        </ul>
      </text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(c)</num>
      <text>As part of this recodification, the Pueblo authorized administrative corrections to replace inaccurate citations and references within the individual resolutions and codes, update renumbering within and between ordinances, correct typos, and make other similar minor changes that do not change the substantive content of the ordinances and codes that are part of the Tribal Code. All such corrections are included as Attachment 1.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <num>2</num>
    <heading>Official Version</heading>
    <text>The electronic version of the Pueblo of Picuris Tribal Law and Order Code, which is published online using OLL software and which is part of the online Pueblo of Picuris Law Library, shall be the official version of such code. Additionally, this Pueblo of Picuris Law Library shall be in the public domain.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <num>3</num>
    <heading>Enactment and Effective Date</heading>
    <text>The Tribe hereby enacts the Pueblo of Picuris Tribal Law and Order Code, which shall become effective on March 11, 2025.</text>
  </section>
  <procedural-data>
    <text>
      <strong>CERTIFICATION</strong>
    </text>
    <text>The Pueblo of Picuris Tribal Council enacted upon the foregoing Resolution on the 11<sup>th</sup> day of March, 2025, by a vote of 7 for, 2 opposed, and 0 abstained, at a duly called meeting at which a quorum of the Pueblo of Picuris Tribal Council was present.</text>
  </procedural-data>
</document>
